<chapter id="running_ccsm">
<title>Running a case</title>

<para> To run a case, the user must submit the batch script
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.run</filename>. In addition, the user needs to
also modify &env_run.xml; for their particular needs. </para>

<para> &env_run.xml; contains variables which may be modified during
the course of a model run. These variables comprise coupler namelist
settings for the model stop time, model restart frequency, coupler
history frequency and a flag to determine if the run should be flagged
as a continuation run. In general, the user needs to only set the
variables $<envar>STOP_OPTION</envar> and $<envar>STOP_N</envar>. The
other coupler settings will then be given consistent and reasonable
default values. These default settings guarantee that restart files
are produced at the end of the model run. </para>


<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect1 id="running_ccsm_runtime">
<title>Customizing runtime settings</title>

<para>
As mentioned above, variables that control runtime settings are found in
&env_run.xml;. In the following, we focus on the handling of run control
(e.g. length of run, continuing a run) and output
data. We also give a more detailed description of &cesm; restarts.
</para>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect2 id="running_ccsm_env_job">
<title>Setting run control variables</title>

<para>
Before a job is submitted to the batch system, the user needs first
check that the batch submission lines in
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.run</filename> are appropriate. These lines
should be checked and modified accordingly for appropriate account
numbers, time limits, and stdout/stderr file names.  The user should
then modify &env_run.xml; to determine the key run-time settings, as
outlined below:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><option>CONTINUE_RUN </option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Determines if the run is a restart run.   
Set to FALSE when initializing a startup, branch or hybrid case.
Set to TRUE when continuing a run. (logical)
</para>
<para>
When you first begin a branch, hybrid or startup run, CONTINUE_RUN
must be set to FALSE. When you successfully run and get a restart
file, you will need to change CONTINUE_RUN to TRUE for the remainder
of your run. Details of <link linkend="running_ccsm_restarts">
performing model restarts </link> are provided below.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>RESUBMIT</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Enables the model to automatically resubmit a new run.  To get
multiple runs, set RESUBMIT greater than 0, then RESUBMIT will be
decremented and the case will be resubmitted.  The case will stop automatically
resubmitting when the RESUBMIT value reaches 0. 
</para>
<para>
Long &cesm; runs can easily outstrip supercomputer queue time limits. For
this reason, a case is usually run as a series of jobs, each
restarting where the previous finished.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>STOP_OPTION</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Ending simulation time. 
</para>
<para>
Valid values are: [none, never, nsteps, nstep, nseconds, nsecond,
nminutes, nminute, nhours, nhour, ndays, nday, nmonths, nmonth,
nyears, nyear, date, ifdays0, end] (char)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>STOP_N</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Provides a numerical count for $STOP_OPTION. (integer)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>STOP_DATE </option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Alternative yyyymmdd date option, negative value implies off. (integer)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>REST_OPTION </option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Restart write interval. 
</para>
<para>
Valid values are: [none, never, nsteps, nstep, nseconds, nsecond,
nminutes, nminute, nhours, nhour, ndays, nday, nmonths, nmonth,
nyears, nyear, date, ifdays0, end] (char)
</para>
<para>
Alternative yyyymmdd date option, negative value implies off. (integer)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>REST_N</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Number of intervals to write a restart. (integer)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>REST_DATE </option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Model date to write restart, yyyymmdd
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>STOP_DATE </option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Alternative yyyymmdd date option, negative value implies off. (integer)
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>
By default,
<screen>
STOP_OPTION = ndays
STOP_N = 5
STOP_DATE = -999
</screen>
</para>

<para>
The default setting is only appropriate for initial testing. Before a 
longer run is started, update the stop times based on the case 
throughput and batch queue limits.  For  example, if the model runs 5 
model years/day, set <envar>RESUBMIT</envar>=30, <envar>STOP_OPTION</envar>= nyears,
and <envar>STOP_N</envar>= 5. 
The model will then run in five year increments, and stop after 30 
submissions.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect2 id="running_ccsm_env_output">
<title>Output data</title>

<para>
Each &cesm; component produces its own output datasets consisting of
history, restart and output log files. Component history files are in
netCDF format whereas component restart files may be in netCDF or
binary format and are used to either exactly restart the model or to
serve as initial conditions for other model cases.
</para>

<para>
Archiving is a phase of a &cesm; model run where the generated output
data is moved from $RUNDIR (normally $EXEROOT/run) to a local disk area (short-term archiving)
and subsequently to a long-term storage system (long-term
archiving). It has no impact on the production run except to clean up
disk space and help manage user quotas.  Short and long-term archiving
environment variables are set in the &env_mach_specific;
file. Although short-term and long-term archiving are implemented
independently in the scripts, there is a dependence between the two
since the short-term archiver must be turned on in order for the
long-term archiver to be activated.  In &env_run.xml;, several
variables control the behavior of short and long-term
archiving. These are described below.
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><option>LOGDIR</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Extra copies of the component log files will be saved here.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>DOUT_S</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
If TRUE, short term archiving will be turned on. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>DOUT_S_ROOT </option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Root directory for short term archiving. This directory must be
visible to compute nodes. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>DOUT_S_SAVE_INT_REST_FILES </option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
If TRUE, perform short term archiving on all interim restart files,
not just those at the end of the run. By default, this value is FALSE.
This is for expert users ONLY and requires expert knowledge. We will
not document this further in this guide.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>DOUT_L_MS</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
If TRUE, perform long-term archiving on the output data. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>DOUT_L_MSROOT</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Root directory on mass store system for long-term data archives.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>DOUT_L_HTAR</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
If true, DOUT_L_HTAR the long-term archiver will store history data in annual tar files.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>DOUT_L_RCP</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
If TRUE, long-term archiving is done via the rcp command
(this is not currently supported).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>DOUT_L_RCP_ROOT</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Root directory for long-term archiving on rcp remote machine.
(this is not currently supported).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>
Several important points need to be made about archiving:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
By default, short-term archiving is enabled and long-term archiving is
disabled.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
All output data is initially written to $RUNDIR.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Unless a user explicitly turns off short-term archiving, files will be
moved to $DOUT_S_ROOT at the end of a successful model run.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> If long-term archiving is enabled, files will be
moved to $<envar>DOUT_L_MSROOT</envar> by
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.l_archive</filename>, which is run as a
separate batch job after the successful completion of a model run.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Users should generally turn off short term-archiving when developing
new &cesm; code.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
If long-term archiving is not enabled, users must monitor quotas and
usage in the $DOUT_S_ROOT/ directory and should manually clean up
these areas on a frequent basis.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>
Standard output generated from each &cesm; component is saved in a "log
file" for each component in $<envar>RUNDIR</envar>. 
Each time the model is run, a
single coordinated datestamp is incorporated in the filenames of all
output log files associated with that run. This common datestamp is
generated by the run script and is of the form YYMMDD-hhmmss, where
YYMMDD are the Year, Month, Day and hhmmss are the hour, minute and
second that the run began (e.g. ocn.log.040526-082714). Log files are
also copied to a user specified directory using the variable $LOGDIR
in &env_run.xml;. The default is a 'logs' subdirectory beneath the
case directory.
</para>

<para>
By default, each component also periodically writes history files
(usually monthly) in netCDF format and also writes netCDF or binary
restart files in the $RUNDIR directory. The history and log files are
controlled independently by each component. History output control
(i.e. output fields and frequency) is set in the
<filename>Buildconf/$component.buildnml.csh</filename> files.
</para>

<para>
The raw history data does not lend itself well to easy time-series
analysis. For example, CAM writes one or more large netCDF history
file(s) at each requested output period.  While this behavior is
optimal for model execution, it makes it difficult to analyze time
series of individual variables without having to access the entire
data volume. Thus, the raw data from major model integrations is
usually postprocessed into more user-friendly configurations, such as
single files containing long time-series of each output fields, and
made available to the community.
</para>

<para>
As an example, for the  following example settings
</para>

<screen>
DOUT_S = TRUE
DOUT_S_ROOT = /ptmp/$user/archive
DOUT_L_MS = TRUE
DOUT_L_MSROOT /USER/csm/b40.B2000
</screen>

<para>
the run will automatically submit the
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.l_archive</filename> to the queue upon its completion to archive the
data.  The system is not bulletproof, and the user will want to verify at regular intervals that
the archived data is complete, particularly during long running jobs.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect1 id="running_ccsm_loadbalance">
<title>Load balancing a case</title>

<para>
Load balancing refers to the optimization of the processor layout for
a given model configuration (compset, grid, etc) such that the cost
and throughput will be optimal. Optimal is a somewhat subjective
thing. For a fixed total number of processors, it means achieving the
maximum throughput. For a given configuration across varied processor
counts, it means finding several "sweet spots" where the model is
minimally idle, the cost is relatively low, and the throughput is
relatively high. As with most models, increasing total processors
normally results in both increased throughput and increased cost. If
models scaled linearly, the cost would remain constant across
different processor counts, but generally, models don't scale linearly
and cost increases with increasing processor count. This is certainly
true for CCSM4. It is strongly recommended that a user perform a
load-balancing exercise on their proposed model run before undertaking
a long production run.
</para>

<para>
CCSM4 has significant flexibility with respect to the layout of
components across different hardware processors. In general, there are
six unique models (atm, lnd, ocn, ice, glc, cpl) that are managed
independently in CCSM4, each with a unique MPI communicator. In
addition, the driver runs on the union of all processors and controls
the sequencing and hardware partitioning.  
</para>

<para>
Please see the section on <link linkend="case_conf_setting_pes">
setting the case PE layout </link> for a detailed discussion of how to
set processor layouts and the example on <link linkend="use_case_pelayout">
changing the PE layout </link>.
</para>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect2 id="timing_info">
<title>Model timing data </title>

<para>
In order to perform a load balancing exercise, the user must first be
aware of the different types of timing information produced by every
&cesm; run. How this information is used is described in detail in 
<link linkend="using_timing_info"> using model timing data. </link>
</para>

<para>
A summary timing output file is produced after every &cesm; run. This
file is placed in
<filename>$CASEROOT/timing/ccsm_timing.$CASE.$date</filename>, where
$date is a datestamp set by &cesm; at runtime, and contains a summary of
various information. The following provides a description of the most
important parts of a timing file.
</para>

<para>
The first section in the timing output, CCSM TIMING PROFILE,
summarizes general timing information for the run. The total run time
and cost is given in several metrics including pe-hrs per simulated
year (cost), simulated years per wall day (thoughput), seconds, and
seconds per model day. This provides general summary information
quickly in several units for analysis and comparison with other
runs. The total run time for each component is also provided, as is the
time for initialization of the model. These times are the aggregate
over the total run and do not take into account any temporal or
processor load imbalances.
</para>

<para>
The second section in the timing output, "DRIVER TIMING FLOWCHART",
provides timing information for the driver in sequential order and
indicates which processors are involved in the cost. Finally, the 
timings for the coupler are broken out at the bottom of the timing
output file.
</para>

<para>
Separately, there is another file in the timing directory,
ccsm_timing_summary.$CASE.$date that accompanies the above timing
summary. This second file provides a summary of the minimum and
maximum of all the model timers.
</para>

<para>
There is one other stream of useful timing information in the
cpl.log.$date file that is produced for every run. The cpl.log file
contains the run time for each model day during the model run. This
diagnostic is output as the model runs. You can search for tStamp in
the cpl.log file to see this information. This timing information is
useful for tracking down temporal variability in model cost either due
to inherent model variability cost (I/O, spin-up, seasonal, etc) or
possibly due to variability due to hardware. The model daily
cost is generally pretty constant unless I/O is written intermittently
such as at the end of the month.  
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect2 id="using_timing_info">
<title>Using model timing data </title>

<para>
In practice, load-balancing requires a number of considerations
such as which components are run, their absolute and relative
resolution; cost, scaling and processor count sweet-spots for each
component; and internal load imbalance within a component. It is often
best to load balance the system with all significant run-time I/O
turned off because this occurs very infrequently (typically one
timestep per month), is best treated as a separate cost, and
can bias interpretation of the overall model load balance. Also, the
use of OpenMP threading in some or all of the components is dependent
on the hardware/OS support as well as whether the system supports
running all MPI and mixed MPI/OpenMP on overlapping processors for
different components. A final point is deciding whether components
should run sequentially, concurrently, or some combination of the two
with each other. Typically, a series of short test runs is done with
the desired production configuration to establish a reasonable load
balance setup for the production job. The timing output can be
used to compare test runs to help determine the optimal load balance.
</para>

<para>
In general, we normally carry out 20-day model runs with restarts
and history turned off in order to find the layout that has the best
load balance for the targeted number of processors.  This provides a
reasonable performance estimate for the production run for most of the
runtime. The end of month history and end of run restart I/O is
treated as a separate cost from the load balance perspective. To setup
this test configuration, create your production case, and then edit
env_run.xml and set STOP_OPTION to ndays, STOP_N to 20, and
RESTART_OPTION to never. Seasonal variation and spin-up costs can
change performance over time, so even after a production run has
started, its worth occasionally reviewing the timing output to see
whether any changes might be made to the layout to improve throughput
or decrease cost.
</para>

<para>
In determining an optimal load balance for a specific 
configuration, two pieces of information are useful. 
</para>

<itemizedlist> 
<listitem><para>
Determine which component or components are most expensive. 
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> Understand the scaling of the individual components,
whether they run faster with all MPI or mixed MPI/OpenMP decomposition
strategies, and their optimal decompositions at each processor
count. If the cost and scaling of the components are unknown, several
short tests can be carried with arbitrary component pe counts just to
establish component scaling and sweet spots.  </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
One method for determining an optimal load balance is as follows
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
start with the most expensive component and a fixed optimal
processor count and decomposition for that component 
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
test the systems, varying the sequencing/concurrency of
the components and the pe counts of the other components
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
identify a few best potential load balance configurations and
then run each a few times to establish run-to-run variability and to
try to statistically establish the faster layout
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
In all cases, the component run times in the timing output file can be
reviewed for both overall throughput and independent component
timings. Using the timing output, idle processors can be identified by
considering the component concurrency in conjunction with the
component timing.
</para>

<para>
In general, there are only a few reasonable concurrency options for CCSM4:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>fully sequential </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>fully sequential except the ocean running concurrently </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>fully sequential except the ice and land running concurrently
with each other </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>atmosphere running sequentially with the land and ice which
are running concurrently and then the ocean running concurrently with
everything </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>finally, it makes best sense for the coupler to run on a
subset of the atmosphere processors and that can be sequentially or
concurrently with the land and ice </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The concurrency is limited in part by the hardwired sequencing in the
driver. This sequencing is set by scientific constraints, although
there may be some addition flexibility with respect to concurrency
when running with mixed active and data models.
</para>

<para>
There are some general rules for finding optimal configurations:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
 Make sure you have set a processor layout where each hardwire
 processor is assigned to at least one component. There is rarely a
 reason to have completely idle processors in your layout.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Make sure your cheapest components keep up with your most expensive
components. In other words, a component that runs on 1024 processors
should not be waiting on a component running on 16 processors.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Before running the job, make sure the batch queue settings in the
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.run</filename> script are set correctly for the specific run being 
targetted.  The account numbers, queue names, time limits should be 
reviewed.  The ideal time limit, queues, and run length are all
dependent on each other and on the current model throughput.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Make sure you are taking full advantage of the hardware resources. If
you are charged by the 32-way node, you might as well target a total
processor count that is a multiple of 32.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
If possible, keep a single component on a single node. That usually
minimizes internal component communication cost. That's obviously not
possible if running on more processors than the size of a node.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
And always assume the hardware performance could have variations due
to contention on the interconnect, file systems, or other areas. If
unsure, run cases multiple times.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect1 id="running_ccsm_running">
<title>The Run</title>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect2 id="running_ccsm_running_timelimit">
<title>Setting the time limits</title>

<para>
Before you can run the job, you need to make sure the batch queue
variables are set correctly for the specific run being targeted. This
is done currently by manually editing
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.run</filename>. The user should carefully check
the batch queue submission lines and make sure that you have
appropriate account numbers, time limits, and stdout file names. In
looking at the ccsm_timing.$CASE.$datestamp files for "Model
Throughput", output like the following will be found:
</para>

<screen>
Overall Metrics:
Model Cost: 327.14 pe-hrs/simulated_year (scale= 0.50)
Model Throughput: 4.70 simulated_years/day
</screen>

<para>
The model throughput is the estimated number of model years that you
can run in a wallclock day. Based on this, the user can maximize
$CASE.$MACH.run queue limit and change $STOP_OPTION and $STOP_N in
&env_run.xml;. For example, say a model's throughput is 4.7
simulated_years/day.  On bluefire, the maximum runtime limit is 6
hours. 4.7 model years/24 hours * 6 hours = 1.17 years. On the
massively parallel computers, there is always some variability in how
long it will take a job to run. On some machines, you may need to
leave as much as 20% buffer time in your run to guarantee that jobs
finish reliably before the time limit. For that reason we will set our
model to run only one model year/job. Continuing to assume that the run is
on bluefire, in <filename>$CASE.bluefire.run</filename> set
</para>

<screen>
#BSUB -W 6:00
</screen>

<para>
and <filename>xmlchange</filename> should be invoked as follows in $CASEROOT:
</para>

<screen>
./xmlchange -file env_run.xml -id STOP_OPTION   -val nyears
./xmlchange -file env_run.xml -id STOP_N        -val 1 
./xmlchange -file env_run.xml -id REST_OPTION   -val nyears
./xmlchange -file env_run.xml -id REST_N        -val 1 
</screen>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect2 id="running_ccsm_running_submit">
<title>Submitting the run</title>

<para>
Once you have configured and built the model, submit
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.run</filename> to your machine's batch queue
system. For example on NCAR's IBM, bluefire,
</para>

<screen>
> # for BLUEFIRE
> bsub < $CASE.bluefire.run
> # for CRAY
> qsub $CASE.jaguar.run
</screen>

<para>
You can see a complete example of how to run a case in <link
linkend="use_case_basic">the basic example</link>.
</para>

<para>
When executed, the run script, <filename>$CASE.$MACH.run</filename>,
will:
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para> Check to verify that the env files are consistent with the
configure and build scripts
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para> Verify that required input data is present on local disk (in
$<envar>DIN_LOC_ROOT_CSMDATA</envar>) and run the buildnml script for
each component
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para> Run the &cesm; model. Put timing information in
<filename>$LOGDIR/timing</filename>.  If $<envar>LOGDIR</envar> is
set, copy log files back to $<envar>LOGDIR</envar>
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para> If $<envar>DOUT_S</envar> is TRUE, component history, log,
diagnostic, and restart files will be moved from
$<envar>RUNDIR</envar> to the short-term archive directory,
$<envar>DOUT_S_ROOT</envar>.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para> If $<envar>DOUT_L_MS</envar> is TRUE, the long-term archiver,
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.l_archive</filename>, will be submitted to the batch queue upon
successful completion of the run.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para> 
If $<envar>RESUBMIT</envar> >0, resubmit <filename>$CASE.$MACH.run</filename>
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>
NOTE: This script does NOT execute the build script,
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.build</filename>. Building &cesm; is now done
only via an interactive call to the build script.
</para>

<para>
If the job runs to completion, you should have "SUCCESSFUL TERMINATION
OF CPL7-CCSM" near the end of your STDOUT file. New data should be in
the subdirectories under $DOUT_S_ROOT, or if you have long-term
archiving turned on, it should be automatically moved to
subdirectories under $DOUT_L_MSROOT.
</para>

<para>
If the job failed, there are several places where you should look for
information. Start with the STDOUT and STDERR file(s) in $CASEROOT. If
you don't find an obvious error message there, the
$RUNDIR/$model.log.$datestamp files will probably give you a
hint. First check cpl.log.$datestamp, because it will often tell you
when the model failed. Then check the rest of the component log
files. Please see <link
linkend="troubleshooting_run_time">troubleshooting runtime
errors</link> for more information.
</para>

<para>
REMINDER: Once you have a successful first run, you must set
CONTINUE_RUN to TRUE in env_run.xml before resubmitting, otherwise the
job will not progress. You may also need to modify the RESUBMIT,
STOP_OPTION, STOP_N, STOP_DATE, REST_OPTION, REST_N and/or REST_DATE
variables in env_run.xml before resubmitting.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect2 id="running_ccsm_restarts">
<title>Restarting a run</title>

<para>
Restart files are written by each active component (and some data
components) at intervals dictated by the driver via the setting of the
&env_run.xml; variables, $<envar>REST_OPTION</envar> and
$<envar>REST_N</envar>. Restart files allow the model to stop and then
start again with bit-for-bit exact capability (i.e. the model output
is exactly the same as if it had never been stopped). The driver
coordinates the writing of restart files as well as the time evolution
of the model.  All components receive restart and stop information
from the driver and write restarts or stop as specified by the driver.
</para>

<para>
It is important to note that runs that are initialized as branch or
hybrid runs, will require restart/initial files from previous model
runs (as specified by the &env_conf.xml; variables,
$<envar>RUN_REFCASE</envar> and $<envar>RUN_REFDATE</envar>).  These
required files must be prestaged <emphasis>by the user</emphasis> to
the case $<envar>RUNDIR</envar> (normally
<filename>$EXEROOT/run</filename>) before the model run starts. This
is normally done by just copying the contents of the relevant
<filename>$RUN_REFCASE/rest/$RUN_REFDATE.00000</filename> directory.
</para>

<para>
Whenever a component writes a restart file, it also writes a restart
pointer file of the form, <filename>rpointer.$component</filename>.
The restart pointer file contains the restart filename that was just
written by the component.  Upon a restart, each component reads its
restart pointer file to determine the filename(s) to read in order to
continue the model run. As examples, the following pointer files will
be created for a component set using full active model components.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>rpointer.atm </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>rpointer.drv </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>rpointer.ice </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>rpointer.lnd </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>rpointer.ocn.ovf </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>rpointer.ocn.restart </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<para>
If short-term archiving is turned on, then the model archives the
component restart datasets and pointer files into
<filename>$DOUT_S_ROOT/rest/yyyy-mm-dd-sssss</filename>, where
yyyy-mm-dd-sssss is the model date at the time of the restart (<link 
linkend="running_ccsm_starch">see below for more details</link>). 
If long-term archiving these restart then
archived in
<filename>$DOUT_L_MSROOT/rest</filename>. <envar>DOUT_S_ROOT</envar>
and <envar>DOUT_L_MSROOT</envar> are set in &env_run.xml;, and can be
changed at any time during the run.
</para>

<sect3 id="running_ccsm_restart_back">
<title>Backing up to a previous restart</title>

<para> If a run encounters problems and crashes, the user will normally have
to back up to a previous restart.  Assuming that short-term archiving
is enabled, the user needs to find the latest
<filename>$DOUT_S_ROOT/rest/yyyy-mm-dd-ssss/</filename> directory that
was create and copy the contents of that directory into their run
directory ($<envar>RUNDIR</envar>). The user can then continue the run
and these restarts will be used.  It is important to make sure the new
rpointer.* files overwrite the rpointer.* files that were in
$<envar>RUNDIR</envar>, or the job may not restart in the correct
place. </para> 

<para> Occasionally, when a run has problems restarting, it is
because the rpointer files are out of sync with the restart files. The
rpointer files are text files and can easily be edited to match the
correct dates of the restart and history files. All the restart files
should have the same date. </para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect2 id="running_ccsm_data_flow">
<title>Data flow during a model run</title>

<para> All component log files are copied to the directory specified
by the &env_run.xml; variable $<envar>LOGDIR</envar> which by default
is set to <filename>$CASEROOT/logs</filename>. This location is
where log files are copied when the job completes successfully.  If the 
job aborts, the log files will NOT be copied out of the <filename>$RUNDIR</filename> directory. 
</para>

<para> Once a model run has completed successfully, the output data
flow will depend on whether or not short-term archiving is enabled (as
set by the &env_run.xml; variable, $<envar>DOUT_S</envar>). By
default, short-term archiving will be done.</para>

<sect3 id="running_ccsm_noarch">
<title>No archiving</title>

<para> If no short-term archiving is performed, then all model output
data will remain in the run directory, as specified by the
&env_run.xml; variable, $<envar>RUNDIR</envar>. Furthermore, if
short-term archiving is disabled, then long-term archiving will not be
allowed. </para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="running_ccsm_starch">
<title>Short-term archiving</title>

<para> If short-term archiving is enabled, the component output files will be
moved to the short term archiving area on local disk, as specified by
$<envar>DOUT_S_ROOT</envar>.  The directory DOUT_S_ROOT is normally  
set to <envar>$EXEROOT/../archive/$CASE</envar>. 
and will
contain the following directory structure: </para>

<screen>
atm/
    hist/ logs/
cpl/ 
    hist/ logs/
glc/ 
    logs/
ice/ 
    hist/ logs/
lnd/ 
    hist/ logs/
ocn/ 
    hist/ logs/
rest/ 
    yyyy-mm-dd-sssss/
    ....
    yyyy-mm-dd-sssss/
</screen>

<para><filename>hist/</filename> contains component history output for
the run.</para>

<para><filename>logs/</filename> contains component log files
created during the run. In addition to $<envar>LOGDIR</envar>, log
files are also copied to the short-term archiving directory and
therefore are available for long-term archiving.</para>

<para>
<filename>rest/</filename> contains a subset of directories that each
contain a <emphasis>consistent</emphasis> set of restart files,
initial files and rpointer files. Each sub-directory has a unique name
corresponding to the model year, month, day and seconds into the day
where the files were created
(e.g. <filename>1852-01-01-00000/</filename>). The contents of any
restart directory can be used to <link linkend="use_case_branch">create a
branch run or a hybrid run</link> or back up to a previous restart
date.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="running_ccsm_ltarch">
<title>Long-term archiving</title>

<para> For long production runs that generate many giga-bytes of data,
the user normally wants to move the output data from local disk to a
long-term archival location. 
Long-term archiving can be activated by setting $<envar>DOUT_L_MS</envar>  
to TRUE in <filename>env_run.xml</filename>. By default, the value of this variable is
FALSE, and long-term archiving is disabled. If the value is set to
TRUE, then the following additional variables are:
$<envar>DOUT_L_MSROOT</envar>, $<envar>DOUT_S_ROOT</envar> <envar>DOUT_S</envar> (see <link
linkend="running_ccsm_env_output"> variables for output data
management</link> ). </para>

<para> As was mentioned above, if long-term archiving is enabled,
files will be moved out of $<envar>DOUT_S_ROOT</envar> to
$<envar>DOUT_L_ROOT</envar> by
<filename>$CASE.$MACH.l_archive</filename>,, which is run as a
separate batch job after the successful completion of a model run.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect1 id="running_ccsm_testing">
<title>Testing a case</title>

<para>
After the case has built and has demonstrated the ability to run via a
short test, it is important to formally test exact
restart capability before a production run is started.
See <xref linkend="create_production_test"/> for
more information about how to use create_production_test.</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
