<chapter id="port">
<title>Porting CCSM</title>

<para> One of the first steps many users will have to address is
getting the CCSM4 model running on their local machine.  This section
addresses that step.  This section will describe two different
ways of going about that.  First, using a generic machine
to setup a case, get that case running, then backing out the new
machine settings.  Second, setting up some new machine settings,
creating a case, testing it, and iterating on the machine settings.
There are similarities and overlap in both
methods.  The generic method is likely to produce a running case
faster.  But eventually, users will want to setup the CCSM4 
scripts so their local machine is supported out-of-the-box.  This
greatly eases setting up cases and benefits groups of users by
requiring the port be done only once.
Finally, some steps to validate the model will be recommended.
</para>

<note>
<para>
When porting using either of the two methods described above, you will want to initially get a dead, X, compset running at a low resolution.  So you could, for instance, start with an X compset at resolution f45_g37.  This allows you to determine whether all prerequisite software is in place and working.  Once that is working move to an A compset with resolution f45_g37.  Once that's working, run a B compset at resolution f45_g37. Finally when all the previous steps have run correctly, run your target compset and resolution. 
</para></note>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->

<sect1 id="port_new">
<title>Porting to a new machine</title>

<sect2 id="port_generic">
<title>Porting using a generic machine</title>

<para>
This section describes how to setup a case using a generic machine name
and then within that case, how to modify the scripts to get that 
case running on a local machine.  In this section, the case name
test1 and the generic machine generic_linux_intel will be
used in the example.  But the specific casename, generic machine, resolution,
and compset to test is at the discretion of the user.  
</para>

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>
Run &create_newcase; choosing a generic machine name that is closest
to the local machine type.  Typing 
<screen>
> create_newcase -l
</screen>
will provide a list of possible machines.  The generic machines start
with the name "generic_".  The generic machines are different from the
supported machines because extra inline documentation is provided and
the user will have to modify some of the resolved scripts.
</para>
<para>
Additional command line arguments are required for the generic machines
to help setup some of the local environment variables.  Typing
<screen>
> create_newcase -h
</screen>
provides a description of the command line arguments.  The &create_newcase; will
look something like this for a generic machine
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts
> create_newcase -case test1 \
                 -res f19_g16 \
                 -compset X \
                 -mach generic_linux_intel \
                 -scratchroot /ptmp/username \
                 -din_loc_root_csmdata /home/ccsm/inputdata \
                 -max_tasks_per_node 8 \
</screen>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Run configure.
<screen>
> cd test1
> configure -case
</screen>
If there are errors at this step, the best approach might be to port starting
from the machine files instead of a generic machine.  See <xref linkend="port_adding_mach"/>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Edit the scripts to be consistent with the local  machine.  Search for "GENERIC_USER" in the scripts.  That
tag will highlight inline documentation and areas that will likely need to be modified.
In particular, modifications will be needed in the following files.
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
env_mach_specific is where modules, paths, or machine environment variables need to be
set.  See the "GENERIC_USER" inline documentation in that file.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Macros.generic_linux_intel is a Macros file for gmake for the system.  In general, that entire file
should be reviewed but there are some particular comments about setting the paths for the
netcdf and mpi external libraries.  See the "GENERIC_USER" inline documentation in that file.
While CCSM supports use of pnetcdf in pio, it's generally best to ignore that feature during
initial porting.  pio works well with standard netcdf.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
test1.generic_linux_intel.run is the job submission script.  Modifications are needed there to address
the local batch environment and the job launch.  See the "GENERIC_USER" inline documentation in that file.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Build the case
<screen>
> ./test1.generic_linux_intel.build
</screen>
This step will often fail if paths to compilers, compiler versions, or libraries are not set properly,
if compiler options are not set properly, or if machine environment variables are not set properly.
Review and edit the env_mach_specific and Macros.generic_linux_intel files, clean the build, 
<screen>
> ./test1.generic_linux_intel.clean_build
</screen>
and try rebuilding again.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Run the job using the local job submission command.  qsub is used here for example.
<screen>
> qsub test1.generic_linux_intel.run
</screen>
The job will fail to submit if the batch commands are not set properly.  The job
could fail to run if the launch command is incorrect or if the batch commands are
not set consistent with the job resource needs.  Review the run script and try
resubmitting.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Once a case is running, then the local setup for the case can be converted into a
specific set of machine files, so future cases can be setup using the user defined
machine name, not the generic machine, and cases should be able to run out-of-the-box.
This step is very similar to the steps associated with porting using user defined
machine files, see <xref linkend="port_adding_mach"/>.
</para><para>
Basically, files in ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines will be added or modified
to support the user defined machine out-of-the-box.  An env_machopts, Macros, and
mkbatch file will be added and the config_machines.xml file will be modified.
First, pick a name that will be associated with the local machine.  Generally, that's the name
of the local machine, but it could be anything.  bugsbunny will be used in the
description to follow and the bugsbunny setup will be based on the test1 example case
above that is running on bugsbunny.  To add bugsbunny to the list of supported machines,
do the following

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Edit ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines/config_machines.xml.  Add an entry for 
bugsbunny.  A good idea is to copy one of the existing entries and then edit it.  
The machine specific env variables that need to be set in 
config_machines.xml for bugsbunny are already set in the env files in the test1 
case directory that was created from the generic machine.  Those values can
be translated directly into the config_machines.xml files for bugsbunny.  That's
a starting point anyway.  In some cases, variables might need to be made more
general.  For instance, the port person's user name and the initial test case
should not appear in the variable definitions.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Copy the env_mach_specific file from the test1 case directory to ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines
as follows
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts/test1
> cp env_mach_specific ../ccsm_utils/Machines/env_machopts.bugsbunny
</screen>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Copy the Macros file from the test1 case directory to ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines as follows
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts/test1
> cp Macros.generic_linux_intel  ../ccsm_utils/Machines/Macros.bugsbunny
</screen>
Then edit the ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines/Macros.bugsbunny file and delete everything
up to the lines
<screen>
#===============================================================================
# The following always need to be set
</screen>
That first section of the Macros file is added automatically when a case is configured so
should not be included in the machine specific setting.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Create a mkbatch.bugsbunny file in ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines.  The easiest way
to do this is probably to copy the mkbatch.generic_linux_intel file from that directory
to mkbatch.bugsbunny 
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines
> cp mkbatch.generic_linux_intel mkbatch.bugsbunny
</screen>
Then edit the mkbatch.bugsbunny to match the changes made in the
test1.generic_linux_intel.run file in the test1 case.  Remove the GENERIC_USER
inline documentation and where that documentation existed, update the batch
commands and job launch commands to be consistent with the test1 run script.
The first part of the mkbatch script computes values that can be used in the
batch commands.  It might require some extra iteration to get this working for
all cases, processor counts, and processor layouts.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Test the new machine setup.  Create a new case based on test1 using the
bugsbunny machine setup
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts
> create_newcase -case test1_bugsbunny \
                 -res f09_g16 \
                 -compset X \
                 -mach bugsbunny 
</screen>
Then configure, build, and run the case and confirm that test1_bugsbunny
runs fine and is consistent with the original test1 case.  Once that works,
test other configurations then move to port validation, see <xref linkend="port_process"/>.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="port_adding_mach">
<title>Porting via user defined machine files</title>

<para>
This section describes how to add support for a new machine 
using machine specific files.  The basic approach is to add support for
the new machine to the CCSM4 scripts directly and then to test and
iterate on that setup.  
Files in ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines will be added or modified
to support the user defined machine out-of-the-box.  An env_machopts, Macros, and
mkbatch file will be added and the config_machines.xml file will be modified.
First, pick a name that will be associated with the local machine.  Generally, that's the name
of the local machine, but it could be anything.  wilycoyote will be used in the
description to follow.  It's also helpful to identify an existing supported
machine that is similar to your machine to use as a starting point in porting.  
If the user defined machine is a linux cluster with an intel compiler, then after reviewing
the current supported machines using
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts
> ./create_newcase -l
</screen>
dublin_intel, hadley, or generic_linux_intel would be good candidates as
starting points.  Starting with a generic machine provides some additional
inline documentation to aid in porting.  If a generic machine is used, search
for the tag "GENERIC_USER" in the scripts for additional documentation.
In the example below, dublin_intel will be used as the
starting point.  To add wilycoyote to the list of supported machines,
do the following
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Edit ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines/config_machines.xml.  Add an entry for 
wilycoyote.  A good idea is to copy one of the existing entries and then edit
the values for wilycoyote.  You could start with the dublin_intel settings although
nearly any machine will be ok.  There are several variable settings here.  The
definition of these variables can be found in the appendix, see <xref linkend="env_case_vars"/>,
<xref linkend="env_conf_vars"/>, <xref linkend="env_mach_pes_vars"/>, <xref linkend="env_build_vars"/>,
and <xref linkend="env_run_vars"/>.
Some of the important ones are MACH which should be set to wilycoyote, EXEROOT
which should be set to a generic working directory like /tmp/scratch/$CCSMUSER/$CASE,
DIN_LOC_ROOT_CSMDATA which should be set to the path to the ccsm inputdata directory,
BATCHQUERY and BATCHJOBS which specify the query and submit command lines
for batch jobs and are used to chain jobs together in production, and MAX_TASKS_PER_NODE
which set the maximum number of tasks allowed on each hardware node.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Copy an env_machopts file to env_machopts.wilycoyote.  Start with the dublin_intel
file.
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines
> cp env_machopts.dublin_intel env_machopts.wilycoyote
</screen>
Edit env_machopts.wilycoyote to change the environment setup, paths, modules, and
environment variables to be consistent with wilycoyote.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Copy a Macros file to Macros.wilycoyote.  Start with the dublin_intel file.
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines
> cp Macros.dublin_intel Macros.wilycoyote
</screen>
Then review and edit the Macros.wilycoyote file as needed.  Pay particular
attention to the compiler name, and the netcdf and mpi paths.  While the compiler
options for a given compiler are pretty consistent across machines, invoking the
compiler and the local paths for libraries are not.
While CCSM supports use of pnetcdf in pio, it's generally best to ignore that feature during
initial porting.  pio works well with standard netcdf.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Copy a mkbatch file to mkbatch.wilycoyote file.  Start with the dublin_intel file.
<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines
> cp mkbatch.dublin_intel mkbatch.wilycoyote
</screen>
Then edit the mkbatch.wilycoyote to be consistent with wilycoyote.  In particular,
the batch commands and the job launching will probably need to be changed.
The batch commands and setup are the first section of the script.  The job
launching can be found by searching for the string "CSM EXECUTION".
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
After an initial pass is made to setup the new machine files, try creating a 
case, building and running.  Getting this to work will be an iterative process.  Changes will
probably be made in both the machine files in ccsm4/scripts/ccsm_utils/Machines
for wilycoyote and in the case as testing proceeds.  Whenever the machine files
are updated, a new case should be setup.  Whenever something is changed in the
case scripts to fix a problem, that change should be migrated back to the wilycoyote
machine files.  In general, it's probably easiest to modify the machine files and
create new cases until the case configures successfully.  Once the case is configuring, 
it's often easiest to edit the case scripts to fix problems in the build and run.
Once a case is running, those changes in the case need to be backed out into
the wilycoyote machine files and then those machine files can be
tested with a new case.

<screen>
> cd ccsm4/scripts
> create_newcase -case test_wily1 \
                 -res f19_g16 \
                 -compset X \
                 -mach wilycoyote 
> cd test_wily1
> configure -case
> ./test_wily1.wilycoyote.build
> qsub test_wily1.wilycoyote.run
</screen>
Eventually, the machine files should work for any user and any configuration
for wilycoyote.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>


</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<sect1 id="port_process">
<title>Port Validation</title>

<para>The following port validation is recommended for any new machine.
Carrying out these steps does not guarantee the model is running properly
in all cases nor that the model is scientifically valid on the new machine.
In addition to these tests, detailed validation should be carried out for
any new production run.  That means verifying that model restarts are
bit-for-bit identical with a baseline run, that the model is bit-for-bit
reproducible when identical cases are run for several months, and that 
production cases are monitored very carefully as they integrate forward
to identify any potential problems as early as possible.  These are 
recommended steps for validating a port and are largely functional tests.
Users are responsible for their own validation process, especially with
respect to science validation.
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Verify functionality by performing these <link linkend="create_test">functionality tests.</link> 
</para>
<screen>
ERS_D.f19_g16.X
ERS_D.T31_g37.A
ERS_D.f19_g16.B1850CN
ERI.f19_g16.X
ERI.T31_g37.A
ERI.f19_g16.B1850CN
ERS.f19_f19.F
ERS.f19_g16.I
ERS.T62_g16.C
ERS.T62_g16.D
ERT.f19_g16.B1850CN
</screen>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para> Verify performance and scaling analysis.</para> 
<orderedlist>

<listitem><para> 
Create one or two <link
linkend="running_ccsm_loadbalance">load-balanced</link> configurations
to check into <filename>Machines/config_pes.xml</filename> for the new
machine.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Verify that performance and scaling are reasonable.</para></listitem> 

<listitem><para> 
Review timing summaries in $&CASEROOT; for load balance and throughput.
</para></listitem> 

<listitem><para> Review coupler "daily" timing output for timing
inconsistencies.  As has been mentioned in the section on <link
linkend="running_ccsm_loadbalance"> load balancing a case </link>,
useful timing information is contained in cpl.log.$date file that is
produced for every run. The cpl.log file contains the run time for
each model day during the model run. This diagnostic is output as the
model runs. You can search for tStamp in this file to see this
information. This timing information is useful for tracking down
temporal variability in model cost either due to inherent model
variability cost (I/O, spin-up, seasonal, etc) or possibly due to
variability due to hardware. The model daily cost is generally
pretty constant unless I/O is written intermittently such as at the
end of the month.

</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para> Perform validation (both functional and scientific):</para>
<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>
Perform a <ulink url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/atm-cam/port/">CAM error growth test</ulink>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Perform a CLM perturbation error growth test (as described in 
the <ulink url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.0/clm/models/lnd/clm/doc/UsersGuide/book1.html">CLM User's Guide</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Follow the <ulink url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.0/cice/validation/index.html">CCSM4.0 CICE port-validation procedure.</ulink>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Follow the <ulink url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.0/pop2/validation/index.html">CCSM4.0 POP2 port-validation procedure.</ulink>
</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Perform two, one-year runs (using the expected load-balanced
configuration) as separate job submissions and verify that
atmosphere history files are bfb for the last month. Do this after
some performance testing is complete; you may also combine this with
the production test by running the first year as a single run and the
second year as a multi-submission production run. This will test
reproducibility, exact restart over the one-year timescale, and
production capability all in one test.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Carry out a 20-30 year 1.9x2.5_gx1v6 resolution, B_1850_CN
compset simulation and compare the results with the diagnostics plots
for the 1.9x2.5_gx1v6 Pre-Industrial Control (see the <ulink
url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/experiments/cesm1.0/diagnostics/">
CCSM4.0 diagnostics </ulink>).  Model output data for these runs will
be available on the <ulink
url="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.0/model_esg/">Earth System
Grid (ESG) </ulink> as well. </para>
</listitem>

</orderedlist>

</sect1>
</chapter>

